<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Astroscopium, or Two hemispheres, containing all the northern and  southern constellations projected upon the poles of the word [sic], according to the observations of Mr. Halley, which (by the help of a moveable horizon) are rendred serviceable in any latitude : the uses of which hemispheres are illustrated by variety of examples : whereunto is added, the antient poetical stories of the stars, shewing reasons why the several shapes and forms are pictures on the coelestical globes.</title>
            <author>Lamb, Francis.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88146</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L205E</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42465</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36282007</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36282007</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150108</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88146)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150108)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2230:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Astroscopium, or Two hemispheres, containing all the northern and  southern constellations projected upon the poles of the word [sic], according to the observations of Mr. Halley, which (by the help of a moveable horizon) are rendred serviceable in any latitude : the uses of which hemispheres are illustrated by variety of examples : whereunto is added, the antient poetical stories of the stars, shewing reasons why the several shapes and forms are pictures on the coelestical globes.</title>
                  <author>Lamb, Francis.</author>
                  <author>Lea, Phillip, fl. 1683-1700.</author>
                  <author>Hood, Thomas, fl. 1582-1598.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition /</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[2], 23, 15-50, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Phillip Lea,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: 1 leaf unsigned, B⁸, A⁴, B-C⁸, D⁴ (D₃, advertisement; D₄ blank)</note>
                  <note>Title within double line border.</note>
                  <note>"Globes, Sphers [sic], Maps, Mathematical Projections, Books and Instruments are made and Sold, by Phillip Lea, at the Atlas and Hercules in Cheapside, near the Corner of Friday street, London"--T.p.</note>
                  <note>"Ancient stories of the several stars and constellations ... Collected from Dr. Hood": p. 15-50.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the William Andrews Clark Memorial Library, University of California, Los Angeles.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astronomical instruments.</term>
               <term>Constellations.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150108:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ASTROSCOPI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>M:</hi> OR TWO Hemiſpheres, Containing all the Northern and Southern CONSTELLATIONS, Projected upon the Poles of the Word.</p>
            <p>According to the Obſervations of Mr. <hi>Halley,</hi> Which (by the help of a Moveable <hi>Horizon</hi>) are rend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Serviceable in any <hi>Latitude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Uſes of which <hi>Hemiſpheres</hi> are Illuſtrated by Variety of <hi>Examples.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Whereunto is added, the Antient <hi>Poetical Stories</hi> of the <hi>Stars;</hi> Shewing Reaſons why the ſeveral Shapes and Forms are Pictured on the <hi>Coeleſtical Globes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Second Edition Corrected By <hi>Phillip Lea.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Heaven</hi>'s <hi>a Book, the Stars are Letters fair,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God is the Writer, Men the Readers are.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Globes, Sphers, Maps, Mathematical Projections,</hi> Books and Inſtruments are made and Sold, by <hi>Phillip Lea,</hi> at the <hi>Atlas</hi> and <hi>Hercules</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide,</hi> near the Corn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of <hi>Friday ſtreet, London.</hi> 1700.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:150108:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150108:2"/>
            <head>THE DESCRIPTION AND USES OF THE <hi>HEMISPHERES.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>EAch of the <hi>Hemiſpheres</hi> conſiſteth of three Pars, one whereof is <hi>Fixed,</hi> and the other two are <hi>Moveable.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Of the Fixed Part</head>
               <p>The <hi>Fixed Circle</hi> is the <hi>Hour Circle</hi> which is divided into 24 equal Parts or Hours, and numbered from XII. on either ſide, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Eaſt and Weſt, by I. II. III, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to XII. on the contrary ſide. And again, each of theſe Hours is ſubdivided into 12 equal Parts, each Part containing 5 minutes of Time.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:150108:3"/>
               <p>Without this Circle of Hours, is another Circle, divided into 32 equal Parts, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominated by the names of the 32 Points of the Mariners Compaſs, diſcovering the Poſition of the <hi>Stars</hi> in the Heavens at any time. And of theſe two Circles, do the Fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Parts of the <hi>Hemiſpheres</hi> conſiſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Of the Moveable Parts.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Within theſe Fixed Circles move the two <hi>Hemiſpheres,</hi> which are limited within two other Circles called <hi>Equinoctials,</hi> which move (with them) upon the Poles of the World, as their Center.</p>
               <p>The innermoſt of which two Circles is divided into 360 equal parts, or degrees, and in a narrow Margine ſo numbered, from the Eaſt, by the South, Weſt, and North, to the Eaſt again, by 10. 20. 30, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to 360— And this Circle, or <hi>Equinoctial,</hi> is again ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divided into 12 equal Parts, each Part con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining 30 deg. or one Sign of the <hi>Zodiack,</hi> and Named by the Names, and Character<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Characters, of the Twelve Signs, thus <hi>ARIES</hi> 10. 20. <hi>Aries</hi> 30, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The outermoſt of theſe two Circles is a Circle of <hi>Months,</hi> and is divided into 12 un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>equal
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150108:3"/>
Parts or <hi>Months,</hi> each <hi>Month</hi> having its Proper Name, and its due number of Days, and are thus named and numbered <hi>JANUARY</hi> 10. 20, 30, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Between the Center of the <hi>Hemiſpheres</hi> (which are the two Poles of the World) and the <hi>Equinoctials,</hi> are inſerted the ſeveral <hi>Stars</hi> according to their <hi>Right Aſcenſions, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations</hi> &amp; <hi>Magnitudes,</hi> the Northern <hi>Stars</hi> upon the Northern, and the Southern upon the Southern <hi>Hemiſphere:</hi> All which <hi>Stars</hi> are drawn into ſuch <hi>Conſtellations</hi> as (by the <hi>Poets</hi>) have been Feigned, or Attributed to them; and ſuch <hi>Stars</hi> as are <hi>In formis,</hi> are there placed, according to their <hi>Right Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Declinations,</hi> and <hi>Magnitudes</hi> alſo.</p>
               <p>From the Center (or Pole) of each <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſphere,</hi> to the beginning of the 360 de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, which is at the beginning (or firſt deg. of <hi>Aries,</hi> is drawn a Semidiameter, which contains one Quarter of the <hi>Equinoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Colure</hi> (and therefore I ſhall ſo call it) which is divided into 90 un-equal degrees, and is numbered from the beginning of <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es</hi> upwards towards the Pole, by 10. 20. 30. 40, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to 90 at the Pole it ſelf.</p>
               <p>Again, from the firſt degree (or begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) of <hi>Aries,</hi> to the beginning of <hi>Libra,</hi> in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150108:4"/>
both <hi>Hemiſpheres,</hi> there is drawn an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Arch of a Circle, which is divided into ſix unequal Parts or Signs, and each Sign is ſubdivided into 30 unequal Parts, of which the Northern <hi>Hemiſphere</hi> contains the ſix Northern, and the Southern the ſix Southern Signs, each Sign being numbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and Charactered thus: <hi>Aries</hi> 10. 20. 30. <hi>Taurus</hi> 10. 20. 30, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Circle is the Ecliptick, and cutteth the Solſticial Colure in the Points <hi>Cancer</hi> and <hi>Capricorn,</hi> which are 23 degrees 30 mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes diſtance from the <hi>Equinoctial</hi> on each <hi>Hemiſphere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is alſo upon the Pole, or Center of each <hi>Hemiſphere,</hi> two Circles deſcribed, the one paſſing through 23 degrees 30 min. and the other through 66 degrees 30 mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes; that which paſſeth through 23 deg. 30 min. in the
<list>
                     <item>Northern <hi>Hemiſphere</hi> is the Tropick of <hi>Cancer,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Southern <hi>Hemiſphere</hi> is the Tropick of <hi>Capricorn,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
and that which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth through 23 degrees 30 minutes of the
<list>
                     <item>Northern <hi>Hemiſphere</hi> is the <hi>Artick</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>Southern <hi>Hemiſphere</hi> is the <hi>Antartick</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
Circle—None of theſe Circles have any diviſions at all upon them, neither is there
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150108:4"/>
any need; but 'by them you may diſcover what <hi>Stars</hi> are bounded and limited by them.</p>
               <p>All theſe parts of the <hi>Hemiſpheres</hi> hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto deſcribed, are general, and are of the ſame uſe in all <hi>Latitudes:</hi> But to make the uſes of theſe <hi>Hemiſpheres</hi> the more ample, there is.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Another <hi>Moveable Part</hi> added, which is an <hi>Horizon,</hi> which <hi>Horizon</hi> muſt be pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to ſome certain <hi>Horizon,</hi> or part of the World, (and although a General or Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal <hi>Horizon</hi> might eaſily be contrived, yet the conveniences thereof would not be equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent to the inconveniences.) And how to make ſuch an <hi>Horizon</hi> for any aſſigned <hi>Place</hi> or <hi>Latitude,</hi> and how to divide the ſame; as alſo to divide the <hi>Equinoctial Colure</hi> and the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> ſhall be ſhewed at the end of this Tracture. In the mean while take notice, that one of the Semidiameters of this particular <hi>Horizon</hi> (as this is here made for the <hi>Latitude</hi> of <hi>London</hi> 51 degrees 30 mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes) is divided and numbered in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, and with the ſame diviſions as is the <hi>Equinoctial Colure.</hi> But the Arch of the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon</hi> is divided, firſt into two equal parts,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150108:5"/>
and each of thoſe numbered by 10. 20. 30. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to 90, from the Eaſt and Weſt Points thereof, to the North and South, and is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain divided into 16 un-equal parts, and named backwards and forwads, from Eaſt and Weſt, by the Denominations of the Points of the Compaſs—This <hi>Horizon</hi> is to be applyed to, and to move upon the Pole, or the Center, of either <hi>Hemiſphere;</hi> and ſo renders the Uſes of the <hi>Hemiſpheres</hi> general for that <hi>Latitude</hi>—Note here, that I call the ſtraight part of the <hi>Horizon</hi> the Diameter, and the Circular part, the Arch of the <hi>Horizon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus have you an accompt of the ſeveral parts of theſe <hi>Hemiſpheres;</hi> it reſteth now, that we ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Uſes of them.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:150108:5"/>
            <head>THE USES OF THE <hi>HEMISPHERES.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 1.</hi> The day of the Month being given to find the <hi>Suns</hi> Place.</head>
               <p>SEek the day of the Month in the <hi>Move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Circle</hi> of Months, and thereto bring the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon;</hi> ſo ſhall it cut in the <hi>Equinoctial,</hi> the Sign, Degree, and Minute, that the <hi>Sun</hi> is then in at Noon, that day.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Example,</hi> Let the day be the 20th. of <hi>April,</hi> and let the <hi>Suns</hi> Place be required— Lay the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon,</hi> upon the 20th. of <hi>April,</hi> and at the ſame time it will
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:150108:6"/>
cut the 10th degree of <hi>Taurus,</hi> which is the <hi>Suns</hi> Place that day. And ſo upon the 8 of <hi>Auguſt</hi> the <hi>Suns</hi> Place will be found to be in 25 deg. and an half of <hi>Leo.</hi> And the 15th of <hi>Novemb.</hi> in 3 deg. 30 min. of <hi>Sagittarius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 2.</hi> The <hi>Suns</hi> Place in the <hi>Zodiack</hi> being given, to find the day of Month.</head>
               <p>BRring the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> to the <hi>Suns</hi> Place, and at the ſame time it will the day of the Month.</p>
               <p>So the Diameter (or a Third) being laid to the 10th deg. of <hi>Taurus,</hi> it will then cut the 20th day of <hi>April:</hi> And laid to 29 deg. and an half of <hi>Leo,</hi> it will cut the 8th day of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> And again laid to 3 deg. 30 min. of <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> it will cut upon the 15th of <hi>November.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 3.</hi> The Place of the <hi>Sun</hi> in the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> being known, to find his Declination.</head>
               <p>FInd the degree of the <hi>Suns</hi> Place in the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> in either of the <hi>Hemiſpheres,</hi> &amp; bring the divided parts of the Diameter
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150108:6"/>
of the <hi>Horizon</hi> thereto; ſo ſhall the degrees of the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon,</hi> which are intercepted by the <hi>Suns</hi> Place in the <hi>Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick,</hi> be the degrees of the <hi>Suns</hi> Declination.</p>
               <p>So if the <hi>Sun</hi> be in 17 deg. of <hi>Taurus,</hi> the divided part of the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> being brought thereto, there will be cut upon the Diameter 17 deg. and that is the <hi>Suns</hi> Declination—Alſo if the <hi>Sun</hi> be in 10 deg. of <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> the Declination will be found to be 22 deg.—And in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of <hi>Piſces,</hi> it will be found 11 deg. and an half.</p>
               <p>And here note, if the <hi>Suns</hi> Place be found in the Northern <hi>Hemiſphere,</hi> the <hi>Suns</hi> Declination is North-ward: But if in the Southern <hi>Hemiſphere,</hi> the Declination is South alſo.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 4.</hi> The <hi>Suns</hi> Declination being given, to find his Place in the <hi>Ecliptick.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF the <hi>Sun</hi> hath North or South Declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, make uſe of the North or South <hi>Hemiſphere</hi>—Then upon the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon,</hi> count the degrees of the <hi>Suns</hi> Declination, and turn the Diameter about
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:150108:7"/>
till the deg. of the <hi>Suns</hi> Declination do croſs the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> and where it ſo croſſeth the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> there is the Place of the <hi>Sun.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So the <hi>Suns</hi> Declination being 10 deg. North, then 10 deg. of the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon,</hi> will cut 25 deg. 55 min. of <hi>Aries,</hi> or 4 deg. 5 min. of <hi>Virgo</hi> in the Northern <hi>Hemiſphere</hi>—And if the <hi>Sun</hi> have 10 deg. of South Declination, it will then cut the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> in 25 deg. 55 min. of <hi>Libia,</hi> or in 4 deg. 5 min. of <hi>Piſces</hi> in the Southern <hi>Hemiſphere.</hi> For the Sun makes four Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of Declination in a Year, in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Quarters of the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> contained be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Colure</hi> and <hi>Colure.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 5.</hi> The Place of the <hi>Sun</hi> being known, to find his Right Aſcenſion.</head>
               <p>BRing the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> to the <hi>Sun</hi>'s Place in the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> then will the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> cut alſo the Circle which is divided into 360 deg. in the degrees of the <hi>Suns</hi> Right Aſcenſion.</p>
               <p>So the <hi>Sun</hi> being 29 deg. of <hi>Taurus,</hi> if you bring the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> to that deg. counted in the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> it will cut
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150108:7"/>
the Circle which is divided into 360 deg. in 56 deg. 50 min. And ſuch is the <hi>Suns</hi> Right Aſcenſion at that time—But if the <hi>Suns</hi> Place had been in 92 deg. of <hi>Scirpio,</hi> then his Right Aſcenſion (in the Southern <hi>Himiſphere</hi> (would be found to be 236 deg. 50 min.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 6.</hi> The <hi>Suns</hi> Diclination being given, to find his Amplitude.</head>
               <p>IN reſolving many <hi>Problems,</hi> it will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to have a Third Fixed in the Center of the <hi>Hemiſpheres;</hi> with a ſmall Bead to move upon it, as in this, and ſome other <hi>Problems</hi> which follow.</p>
               <p>Firſt, lay the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> upon the two Sixes; and ſet the Bead which is upon the third to the <hi>Suns</hi> Declination, counted upon the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon:</hi> Then move the Third along till the Bead do juſt touch the Arch of the <hi>Horizon,</hi> and what degrees of the Arch the <hi>Horizon</hi> the Bead chanceth to fall upon, thoſe degrees (or that Point of the Compaſs) counted from the Eaſt and Weſt Points of the <hi>Hori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zon,</hi> are the degrees of the <hi>Suns</hi> Amplitude
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150108:8"/>
or Diſtance of his Riſing or his Setting, from the true Eaſt or Weſt Point.</p>
               <p>So the <hi>Sun</hi> having 23 deg. 30 min. of North Declination, ſet the Bead thereto; and (the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> lying juſt upon VI and VI) move the Thred till the Bead upon it do juſt touch the Arch of the <hi>Horizon;</hi> which it will do at 40 deg. (or within 6 deg. and a Quarter of the North-Eaſt or North-Weſt Points of the Compaſs) which is the <hi>Suns</hi> Amplitude—But if the <hi>Suns</hi> Declination had been 20 deg. the Bead ſet thereto, and moved to the Arch of the <hi>Horizon,</hi> it would then cut 33 deg. 20 min. (or 25 min. ſhort of the North-Eaſt by Eaſt, or South-Weſt by South Points of the Compaſs) for the Amplitude.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 7.</hi> The <hi>Suns</hi> Declination given, to find the time of the <hi>Suns</hi> Riſing and Setting.</head>
               <p>REctifie the Bead to the Declination, and lay the <hi>Horizon</hi> to the two Sixes, as before; then move the Thred till the Bead touch the Arch of the <hi>Horizon;</hi> and then ſhall the Thred ſhew upon the Hour Circle, the Hout and minute of the <hi>Suns</hi> Riſing or Setting.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:150108:8"/>So the Declination being 23 deg. 30 min. the Bead rectified, and brought to the Arch of the <hi>Horizon,</hi> the Thred will then cut the Hour Circle at 47 min. after III in the Morning, at which time the <hi>Sun</hi> Riſeth; and if you carry the String yet on, till the Bead touch the Arch of the <hi>Horizon</hi> in the other ſide of XII. the Thred will then fall upon 13 min. after VIII. at Night; at which time the <hi>Sun</hi> Setteth—But if the <hi>Sun</hi> have 20 deg. of North Declination, you ſhall find that he will Riſe 11 min. after IV and Set at 49 min. after VII.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 8.</hi> How to find the Right Aſcenſion of any <hi>Star.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOve the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, till it lie upon the Center of the <hi>Star;</hi> and upon the Circle of 360 deg. the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> ſhall there ſhew the degrees of Right Aſcenſion.</p>
               <p>So the Diameter being laid upon <hi>Cor Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis,</hi> ſhall cut 147 deg. 17 min.—And laid upon the <hi>Bulls-Eye,</hi> it ſhall cut 64 deg. 17 min. which are the Right Aſcenſions of thoſe <hi>Stars.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="problem">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:150108:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 9.</hi> To find the Declination of a <hi>Star.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>MOve the Graduated Part of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> about, till it cut the <hi>Star</hi> deſired, and count what degrees of the Diameter are cut by the <hi>Star,</hi> for thoſe are the degrees of the <hi>Stars</hi> Declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
               <p>So if the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> be brought about till it touch <hi>Cor Leonis,</hi> that <hi>Star</hi> ſhall be cut by 13 deg. 33 min. which is that <hi>Stars</hi> Declination— And the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ameter being turned about to the <hi>Bulls-Eye,</hi> that <hi>Star</hi> ſhall be cut by 15 deg. 46 min. and that is his Declination</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 10.</hi> To find what <hi>Stars</hi> do never Set, but are always above the <hi>Horizon</hi> in any <hi>Latitude.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Count your <hi>Latitude</hi> upon the Graduated Diameter of the <hi>Horizon,</hi> from the Pole or Center down wards, (calling 80 deg. 10 deg. and 70 deg. 20 deg. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (So keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Finger, ot ſetting a Pin, in that Point, turn the <hi>Horizon</hi> round about, and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150108:9"/>
all thoſe <hi>Stars</hi> which are between your Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and the Pole, do never Riſe nor Set, but are always above that <hi>Horizon</hi>—And all ſuch <hi>Stars</hi> whoſe Declination are greater then the Complement of any <hi>Latitude,</hi> do never Riſe or Set in that <hi>Latitude</hi>— And all ſuch <hi>Stars</hi> in the contrary <hi>Hemiſphere;</hi> whoſe Declination do exceed the <hi>Latitude,</hi> thoſe <hi>Stars</hi> do never Riſe, or appear in that <hi>Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus, if you lay the Diameter to <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cida Lyra,</hi> you ſhall find that <hi>Star</hi> to lie juſt under 51 deg. 30 min. (if you count the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees from the Pole downwards) ſo that in the <hi>Latitude of</hi> 51 deg. 30 min. when that <hi>Star</hi> is to the Weſt-ward of the South part of the Meridian, it continually Deſcends Lower and Lower, till being Arrived to the North part of the Meridian; and then it immediately begins to Aſcend, till it Arrives to the Southern part of the Meridian again.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 11.</hi> To find the <hi>Longitude</hi> of any <hi>Star,</hi> or any <hi>Stars</hi> Place in the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LAy a String, or Rule, from the Pole of the <hi>Ecliptick,</hi> (which is marked in each
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150108:10"/>
                  <hi>Hemiſphere</hi> dy the Character ☉, and is at the Interſections of the <hi>Solſticial Colures,</hi> with the <hi>Artick</hi> and <hi>Antartick</hi> Circles) to the Center of the <hi>Star</hi> whoſe <hi>Longitude</hi> is required; and ſo ſhall the String or Ruler cut in the <hi>Eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick Line,</hi> and alſo in the <hi>Equinoctial,</hi> the Sign and degree of the <hi>Stars Longitude.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>So a Ruler laid from ☉ (the Pole of the <hi>Eclptick</hi>) to <hi>Aldebaron,</hi> or the <hi>Bulls-Eye</hi> it will cut both the <hi>Eqinoctial</hi> and <hi>Ecliptick</hi>-Circles in 5 deg. 31 min. of <hi>Gemini,</hi> or in 65 deg. 12 min. of the Circle of 360 deg.— And laid from the Pole of the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> ☉, to the <hi>Lions Tail,</hi> it ſhall cut the <hi>Ecliptick</hi> and <hi>Equinoctial,</hi> both of them in 19 deg. of <hi>Virgo,</hi> or in 169 deg. of the Circle of 360 deg.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 12.</hi> To know what <hi>Stars</hi> ſhall be upon the Meridian at any Hour of the Night throughout the Year.</head>
               <p>LAy the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> upon XII. and XII. and move the <hi>Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere</hi> about, till you bring the Day of the Month juſt againſt the propoſed Hour, ſo ſhall all thoſe <hi>Stars</hi> which lie under the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ameter of the <hi>Horizon,</hi> be upon the Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an at that Hour of the Night.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:150108:10"/>Thus, if it were required to know what <hi>Stars</hi> ſhall be upon the Meridian upon the 14th. of <hi>January,</hi> at 8 of the Clock.</p>
               <p>Lay the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> upon XII. and XII. then turn the <hi>Hemiſphere</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, till you bring the 14th. day of <hi>January</hi> to lie juſt againſt VIII. in the Hour Circle; then will all thoſe <hi>Stars</hi> which lie juſt under the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon,</hi> be upon the Meridian at VIII. of the Clock that Night, of which you ſhall find <hi>Aldebaron,</hi> or the <hi>Bulls-Eye</hi> to be the Principal.—And at 4 minutes after XI. that Night will the <hi>Little Dog</hi> be upon the Meridian.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 13.</hi> To know what <hi>Stars</hi> will be upon the Meridian at Midnight, any Night in the Year.</head>
               <p>LAy the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> upon the Day of the Month, ſo ſhall all the <hi>Stars</hi> which lie under the Diameter be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Meridian at XII. of the Clock.— This needeth no Example, but you may find, that upon
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Feb.</hi> 6. the <hi>Lions Heart</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Feb.</hi> 16. the <hi>Lions Back</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>March</hi> 3. the <hi>Lions Tail</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>March</hi> 27. the <hi>Virgins Spike</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
will be upon the Meridian at XII. at Night, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="problem">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:150108:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 14.</hi> To know at what Hour of the Night any <hi>Star</hi> will be upon the Meridian.</head>
               <p>LAy the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> upon XII. and move the <hi>Hemiſphere</hi> about, till the <hi>Bulls-Eye</hi> lies juſt under the Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, then juſt againſt the firſt day of <hi>January</hi> in the Circle of Months you ſhall find 55 Minutes paſt VIII. in the Hour Circle, which ſhews, that at that time the <hi>Bulls-Eye</hi> will be upon the Meridian.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 15.</hi> To find the difference of <hi>Longitude,</hi> or the <hi>Horary</hi> Diſtance of any two <hi>Stars.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BRing one of the <hi>Stars</hi> againſt XII. in the Hour Circle, then lay the Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> upon the other <hi>Star;</hi> and what Hour that cuts (counted from XII.) upon the Hour Circle, is the Diſtance of <hi>Longitude,</hi> or <hi>Horary</hi> Diſtance of theſe two Stars.</p>
               <p>Thus, Let the two Stars be the <hi>Bulls-Eye,</hi> and the <hi>Lions Tail.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:150108:11"/>
               <p>Bring the <hi>Lions Tail</hi> to XII. and then if you lay the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> upon the <hi>Bulls-Eye,</hi> you ſhall find it to cut 7 Hours and 15 minutes, which is 109 degrees; and ſuch is the difference of <hi>Longitude</hi> of theſe two Stars, or their <hi>Horary</hi> Diſtance.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 16.</hi> To find the Hour of the Night by the <hi>Stars.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SEE what <hi>Star</hi> you find to be either up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the North, or South part of the Meridian; and accordingly bring the ſame Star to the like Meridian in the <hi>Hemiſphere:</hi> Then look the day of the Month in the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of Months, right againſt which you have the true Hour of the Night.</p>
               <p>Thus, if upon the 20th. of <hi>January</hi> you ſhould find <hi>Aldebaron,</hi> or the <hi>Bulls-Eye</hi> to be upon the South part of the Meridian; bring <hi>Aldebaron</hi> juſt againſt XII. in the <hi>Hemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſphere,</hi> then againſt the 20th. of <hi>January</hi> you ſhall find 22 Minutes before 8. or 38 Minutes after 7. which is the true Hour of the Night on the 20th. of <hi>January,</hi> when <hi>Aldebaron</hi> will be upon the Meridian.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="problem">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:150108:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 17.</hi> To find the Semidiurnal, or Seminocturnal Arch of any <hi>Star.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>LAy the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> upon VI. and bring the <hi>Star</hi> juſtly to touch the Arch of the <hi>Horizon:</hi> Then lay the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> upon the <hi>Star,</hi> and count how many Hours are contained be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween either of the XII<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. for the one is the Semidiurnal, and the other the Seminoctur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Arch of that <hi>Star.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, if you lay the Diameter of the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon</hi> upon VI. and bring <hi>Aldebaron</hi> to touch the Arch of the <hi>Hoizon;</hi> and then lay the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> upon <hi>Aldebaron,</hi> you ſhall find it to cut upon 36 minutes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter IIII. if you count the Hours from XII. ſo that the Seminocturnal Arch of that <hi>Star</hi> is 4 Hours 36 minutes: And if you counr the Hours from the other XII. you ſhall find them to be 7 Hours 24 minutes, which is the Semidiurnal Arch of that <hi>Star,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Star</hi> having North Declination.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="problem">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:150108:12"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 18.</hi> To find the Amplitude, or the Point of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs upon which any <hi>Star</hi> Riſeth or Setteth.</head>
               <p>LAy the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> upon VI. and bring the Star to touch the Arch of the <hi>Horizon,</hi> ſo ſhall the degrees of the Arch of the <hi>Horizon</hi> contained between the Eaſt or Weſt Points of the <hi>Horizon,</hi> ſhew the Amplitude of that Stars Riſing and Setting, from the Eaſt or Weſt, towards the North or South.</p>
               <p>Thus, If you lay the Diameter of the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizon</hi> upon VI. and bring the <hi>Bulls-Eye</hi> to the Arch therefore, you ſhall find it to lie under 26 degrees of the <hi>Horizon;</hi> and ſo many de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees doth that Star Riſe diſtance from the true Eaſt Point towards the North, and Sets ſo many degrees diſtance from the Weſt North-ward alſo, (becauſe the Star hath North Declination) and ſo his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plitude of Riſing is North-Eaſt by Eaſt 8 degrees Eaſterly. And his Amplitude of Setting is North-Weſt by Weſt 8 degrees Weſterly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="problem">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:150108:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 19.</hi> To find at what Hour any <hi>Star</hi> Riſeth or Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.</head>
               <p>LAy the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> upon VI. and bring the Star to lie juſt under the Arch of the <hi>Horizon</hi> on the Eaſt ſide. Then ſeek the day of the Month in the Circle of Months, and the Hour which ſtandeth againſt it, is the Hour of the Stars Riſing: And if you bring the Star to lie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Arch of the <hi>Horizon</hi> on the Weſt ſide againſt the day of the Month, you ſhall have the time of the Stars Setting.</p>
               <p>Thus, upon the 25th. of <hi>December,</hi> if you would know at what Hour the <hi>Bulls-Eye</hi> Riſeth and Sets. Lay the Diameter of the <hi>Horizon</hi> upon VI. and bring the <hi>Bulls-Eye</hi> juſt under the Arch of the <hi>Horizon</hi> on the Eaſt ſide, and againſt the day of the Month you ſhall find II Hours from the Meridian, which is 2 of the Clock in the Afternoon for the time of that Stars Riſing. And the Star being brought under the Weſt part of the <hi>Horizon,</hi> the day of the Month ſhall be againſt IIII Hours 46 minutes, which is 46 minutes after 4 in the Morning, at which
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150108:13"/>
Hour <hi>Aldebaron,</hi> or the <hi>Bulls-Eye</hi> Setteth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="problem">
               <head>
                  <hi>Probl. 20.</hi> To know what time of the Year any <hi>Star</hi> in the <hi>Hemiſphere</hi> will be upon the Meridian at <hi>12</hi> a Clock at Night.</head>
               <p>BRing the Star to XII on the South part of the Meridian, then upon that day of the Month which ſtandeth againſt the North XII. ſhall that Star be upon the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian at Midnight.</p>
               <div type="example">
                  <head>Example.</head>
                  <p>I would know upon what Night in the Year the <hi>Bulls-Eye</hi> will be upon the Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an at 12 at Night: Bring the <hi>Bulls-Eye</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the South XII. and againſt the North XII. you ſhall find the 16th. of <hi>November,</hi> upon which Night at 12 of the Clock <hi>Alde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baron</hi> (or the <hi>Bulls-Eye</hi>) will be upon the Meridian.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:150108:14"/>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:150108:14"/>
            <head>Here follows the ANCIENT STORIES Of the ſeveral Stars and Conſtellations. Shewing the Poetical Reaſons why ſuch Various FIGURES are placed in HEAVEN.</head>
            <head type="sub">Collected from Dr. <hi>HOOD.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>And Firſt, <hi>Of the</hi> Northern Conſtellations.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>URSA MINOR,</hi> This Conſtellation hath the preheminence, becauſe it is neareſt of all the reſt unto the North Pole; and is called of the <hi>Greeks Arctos,</hi> whereupon the Pole is called the Pole Artick, for that it is near unto this Conſtellation. It is alſo called <hi>Helice minor,</hi> becauſe of the ſmall Revolution which it maketh round about the Pole: or rather of <hi>Elice,</hi> a Town in <hi>Arcadia,</hi> wherein <hi>Caliſto</hi> the great Bear, and Mother to the leſs, was bred. It is called
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150108:15"/>
                  <hi>Cynoſura,</hi> becauſe this Conſtellation, though it car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the name of a Bear, yet it hath the tail of a Dog: Laſt of all, it is termed <hi>Phoenice,</hi> becauſe that <hi>Thales,</hi> who firſt gave the name to this Conſtellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, was a <hi>Phoenician:</hi> And therefore the <hi>Phoenicians</hi> being taught how to uſe it in their Navigations, did call it by the name of the Countrey wherein <hi>Thales</hi> was born: It conſiſteth of Seven Stars, which the Latines call <hi>Septentriones,</hi> becauſe by their continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al motions thoſe Seven Stars do as it were wear the Heaven. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> do call them all <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſina,</hi> that is an <hi>Horn;</hi> becauſe they may be very well brought into that form; whereof that which is the end of the Tail is called the <hi>Pole-Star,</hi> by reaſon of the nearneſs thereof unto the Pole of the World; for it is diſtant (according to the opinion of moſt) from the true Pole, but 3 degrees 30 mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes. The <hi>Arabians</hi> call it <hi>Alrukaba.</hi> And of the <hi>Scythians</hi> it is ſaid to be an <hi>Iron nail,</hi> and is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped by them as a God. The two Stars that are in the ſhoulders of the <hi>Bear,</hi> are called the <hi>Guards,</hi> of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> word <hi>Guardare,</hi> which is to behold; becauſe they are diligently to be looked unto, in regard of their ſingular uſe which they have in Navigation.</p>
               <p>The reaſon why this Conſtellation was brought into the Heavens is diverſly ſet down, and firſt in this manner; <hi>Saturn</hi> having received of the Oracle that one of his Sons ſhould baniſh him out of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, determined with himſelf to kill all the Men-children that he ſhould beget; whereupon he gave command to <hi>Ops</hi> his Wife, being then great, that ſhe ſhould ſhew him the Child ſo ſoon as ever it was
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:150108:15"/>
born: But ſhe bringing forth <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and being greatly delighted with his hair, gave the Child unto two Nymphs of <hi>Creet,</hi> dwelling in the Mount <hi>Dicte,</hi> whereof this was one, and was called <hi>Cynoſura,</hi> the other was <hi>Helice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jupiter,</hi> after that (according to the Oracle) he had bereft his Father of his Kingdom, in recompence of their pains and curteſy, tranſlated them both into the Heavens, and made of them two Conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the <hi>leſſer Bear,</hi> and the <hi>greater Bear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Other-ſome ſay, that it was <hi>Arcas</hi> the ſon of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>listo,</hi> and they tell the Tale on this manner; <hi>Caliſto</hi> a Nymph of ſingular Beauty, Daughter to <hi>Lycaon</hi> King of <hi>Arcadia,</hi> induced by the great deſire ſhe had of hunting, became a follower of the Goddeſs <hi>Diana.</hi> After this, <hi>Jupiter</hi> being enamoured with her Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and out of hope, by reaſon of her profeſſion, to win her love, in his own perſon, counterfeited the ſhape of <hi>Diana,</hi> lay with <hi>Caliſta,</hi> and got her with Child, of whom was born a Son which was called <hi>Arcas. Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> or rather <hi>Juno,</hi> being very much offended here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, turned <hi>Caliſto</hi> into a <hi>Bear. Arcas</hi> her Son at the age of fifteen, hunting in the Woods, by chance light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on his Mother in the ſhape of a <hi>Bear,</hi> who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Son <hi>Arcas,</hi> ſtood ſtill that he might come near unto her, and not be afraid: but he fearing the ſhape of ſo cruel a Beaſt, bent his Bow of purpoſe to have ſlain her: whereupon <hi>Jupiter</hi> to prevent the miſchief, tranſlated them both into Heaven, and of them made two ſeveral Conſtellations: unto the <hi>Leſſer Bear</hi> there belongs but one Star unformed.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RSA MAJOR,</hi> the <hi>Greater Bear,</hi> called alſo of the Greeks <hi>Arctos,</hi> and <hi>Helice,</hi> conſiſteth of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:150108:16"/>
27 Stars; Among the which, thoſe ſeven that are in the hinder part and tail of the Bear are moſt obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; the Latines call them <hi>Plauſtrum,</hi> and of our men they are called <hi>Charles Wayn;</hi> becauſe the Stars do ſtand in ſuch ſort, that the three which are in the tail reſemble the Horſes, and the other four which are in the flank of the <hi>Bear,</hi> ſtand (after a manner) like the Wheels of a wagon, or Chariot; and they are ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by ſome to be greater than the Sun. The reaſon of the tranſlation of this Conſtellation into the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, is at large ſet down in the other Conſtellation, and therefore needs not here to be repeated. This Conſtellation was firſt invented by <hi>Nauplius,</hi> the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Palamedes</hi> the Greek; and in great uſe among the Grecians; and this is to be noted both in this and the former Conſtellation, that <hi>they never ſet under the Horizon in any part of Europe:</hi> which though it fall out by reaſon of their ſcituation in the Heavens; Yet the Poets ſay, that it came to paſs through the diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure and hatred of <hi>Juno,</hi> who for that ſhe was by <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſto</hi> made a Cuckquean, and they notwithſtanding (as ſhe took it) in deſpight of her were Tranſlated into Heaven, requeſted her brother <hi>Neptune,</hi> that he ſhould never ſuffer thoſe Stars to ſet within his Kingdom, To which requeſt <hi>Neptune</hi> condeſcended; ſo that in all Europe they never come near unto the Sea, or touch the Horizon. If any one marvel, that (ſeeing ſhe hath the form of a <hi>Bear</hi>) ſhe ſhould have a tail ſo long; imagine that <hi>Jupiter</hi> fearing to come too nigh unto her teeth, laid hold on her tail, and thereby drew her up into Heaven; ſo that ſhe of her ſelf being very weighty, and the diſtance from the Earth to the Heaven very great, there was great like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyhood
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150108:16"/>
that her tail muſt ſtretch. The Unformed Stars belonging to this Conſtellation are Eight.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>DRACO,</hi> the <hi>Dragon,</hi> of ſome named the <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent;</hi> of others the <hi>Snake,</hi> by the <hi>Arabians, Aben,</hi> and by <hi>Junctinus Florentinus, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rago;</hi> becauſe he windeth his tail round about the Ecliptick Pole; it contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth 31 Stars. This was the Dragon that kept the Golden Apples in the Orchard of the <hi>Heſperides,</hi> (now thought to be the Iſlands of <hi>Cape de Virde</hi>) and for his diligence and watchfulneſs, was afterwards Tranſlated into Heaven: Yet others ſay that he came into Heaven by this occaſion; when <hi>Minerva</hi> withſtood the <hi>Gyants</hi> fighting againſt the <hi>Gods;</hi> they to terrifie her, threw at her a mighty <hi>Dragon,</hi> but ſhe catching him in her hands, threw him pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently up into Heaven, and placed him there, as a memorial of that her reſiſtance. Others would have it to be the Serpent <hi>Python,</hi> whom <hi>Apollo</hi> ſlew, after the Deluge.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>CEPHE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> containeth in him 11 Stars, and hath two unformed. This was a King of the <hi>Aethi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opians,</hi> and Husband unto <hi>Caſſiopeia,</hi> and Father of <hi>Andromeda,</hi> whom <hi>Perſeus</hi> married: He was taken up into Heaven, with his Wife and Daughter, for the good Deeds of <hi>Perſeus</hi> his Son in Law, that he and his whole ſtock might be had in remembrance for ever. The Star which is in his right ſhoulder is called by the <hi>Arabians Alderahiemin</hi> (i. e.) his right Arm.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>BOOTES, the driver of the Oxen</hi> (for ſo I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the name to ſignifie, rather than an <hi>Herdſman,</hi> for he hath not his name becauſe he hath the care of any Cattel, but only becauſe he is ſuppoſed to drive
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150108:17"/>
                  <hi>Charles his Wain,</hi> which is drawn by 3 Oxen) he is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo called <hi>Arctophilax,</hi> the keeper of the <hi>Bear,</hi> as tho' the care of her were committed to him: This Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation conſiſteth of 22 Stars. Some will have <hi>Bootes</hi> to be <hi>Arcas,</hi> the Son of her who before was turned into the <hi>Great Bear;</hi> and they tell the Tale thus: <hi>Lycaon</hi> the Father of <hi>Caliſto,</hi> receiving <hi>Jupiter</hi> into his houſe as a Gueſt, took <hi>Arcas</hi> his Daughters Son, and cut him in pieces; and among other Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſet him before <hi>Jupiter</hi> to be eaten; for by this means he thought to prove if his Gueſt were a God, as he pretended to be <hi>Jupiter</hi> perceiving this heinous fact, overthrew the Table, fired the houſe with lightning, and turned <hi>Lycaon</hi> into a Wolf: but gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, &amp; ſetting together again the limbs of the child, he committed him to a Nimph of <hi>Aetolia</hi> to be kept: <hi>Arcas</hi> afterwards coming to mans eſtate, and hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Woods, lighted at un-awares upon his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, transformed by <hi>Juno</hi> into the ſhape of a <hi>Bear,</hi> whom he purſued into the Temple of <hi>Jupiter Lycae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> whereunto by the Law of the <hi>Arcadians,</hi> it was death for any man to come. For as much therefore as they muſt of likelihood be both ſlain, <hi>Caliſto</hi> by her Son, and he by the Law, <hi>Jupiter</hi> to avoid this miſchief, of meer pity took them both up into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Unto this Conſtellation belongeth but one Star unformed, and it is between the legs of <hi>Bootes,</hi> and by the <hi>Grecians</hi> it is called <hi>Arcturus,</hi> becauſe of all the ſtars near the great <hi>Bear</hi> named <hi>Arctos,</hi> this ſtar is firſt ſeen near her tail in the evening. The Poetical invention is thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Icarus</hi> the Father of <hi>Erigone,</hi> having received of the God <hi>Bacchus</hi> a Flagon of Wine, to declare how good
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150108:17"/>
it was for mortal men, travelled therewith into the Territoires of <hi>Athens,</hi> and there began to carouſe with certain ſhepheards, they being greatly delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the pleaſantneſs of the wine, being a new kind of Liquor, began to draw ſo hard at it, that er'e they left off, they were paſt one and thirty; and in the end, were fain to lay their heads to reſt. But coming unto themſelves again, and finding their brains ſcarce in good temper, they kil'd <hi>Icarus,</hi> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed that he had either poyſoned them, or at the leaſt-wiſe made their brains intoxicate. <hi>Erigone</hi> was ready to dye for grief, and ſo was <hi>Mera</hi> her lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle dog. But <hi>Jupiter</hi> to allay their grief, placed her Father in Heaven, between the legs of <hi>Arctophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lax.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>CORONA BOREA,</hi> the <hi>Northern Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> conſiſteth of Eight Stars; yet <hi>Ovid</hi> ſaith, that it hath nine. This was the Garland that <hi>Venus</hi> gave unto <hi>Ariadne,</hi> when ſhe was Married unto <hi>Bacchus,</hi> in the Iſle <hi>Naxus,</hi> after that <hi>Theſeus</hi> had forſaken her: which garland <hi>Bacchus</hi> placed in the Heaven; as a token of his love. <hi>Novidius</hi> will have it to be the <hi>Crown of the Virgin Mary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>ENGONASIS;</hi> This Conſtellation hath the name, becauſe it is expreſſed under the ſhape of a man kneeling upon the one knee, and is therefore by the Latines called <hi>Ingeniculum</hi> It containeth 29 Stars and wanteth a proper Name, becauſe of the great diverſity of Opinions concerning the ſame. For ſome will have it to be <hi>Hercules,</hi> that mighty Conqueror who for his 12 Labours was thought worthy to be placed in the Heaven, and nigh unto the <hi>Dragon</hi> whom he overcame. Others tell the tale thus: That
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150108:18"/>
when the <hi>Tytans</hi> fought againſt the <hi>Gods,</hi> they for fear of the <hi>Gyants,</hi> ran all unto the one ſide of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven: whereupon the Heaven was ready to have fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len, had not <hi>Hercules</hi> together with <hi>Atlas,</hi> ſet his neck unto it, and ſtayed the fall: and for his Deſert he was placed in Heaven.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>LYRA,</hi> the <hi>Harp,</hi> it containeth 10 Stars, whereof thus goeth the Fable. The River <hi>Nilus</hi> ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling above his banks, over-flowed the Country of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt;</hi> after the fall whereof there were left in the fields divers kinds of living things, and amongſt the reſt a <hi>Tortoiſe; Mercury,</hi> after the fleſh thereof was conſumed, the ſinews ſtill remaining, found the ſame, and ſtriking it, he made it yield a certain ſound; whereupon he made an <hi>Harp</hi> like unto it, having Three ſtrings, and gave it unto <hi>Orpheus</hi> the Son of <hi>Caſſiopea.</hi> This <hi>Harp</hi> was of ſuch excellent ſound, that Trees, Stones, Fowls, and Wild Beaſts are ſaid to follow the ſound thereof. After ſuch time therefore that <hi>Orpheus</hi> was ſlain by the Women of <hi>Thrace</hi> the Muſes by the good leave of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and at the requeſt of <hi>Apollo,</hi> placed this <hi>Harp</hi> in Heaven<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Novidius</hi> will have it to be the <hi>Harp</hi> of <hi>David,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he pacified the Evil ſpirit of <hi>Saul.</hi> This Conſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation was afterwards called <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ultur Cadens,</hi> the <hi>fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Grype:</hi> and <hi>Falco</hi> the <hi>Falcon;</hi> or <hi>Timpanum</hi> the <hi>Timbrel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>OLOR,</hi> or <hi>Cygnus</hi> the <hi>Swan,</hi> called of the Chaldaeans <hi>Adigege,</hi> it hath 17 Stars: of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation the Poets Fable in this manner. <hi>Jupiter</hi> being overtaken with the love of <hi>Laeda</hi> the wife of <hi>Tyndarus</hi> King of <hi>Oebalia,</hi> and knowing no honeſter way to accompliſh his deſire, procured <hi>Venus</hi> to turn
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150108:18"/>
her ſelf into an <hi>Eagle,</hi> and himſelf he turned into the ſhape of a <hi>Swan.</hi> Flying therefore from the <hi>Eagle,</hi> as from his natural Enemy that earneſtly purſued him he lighted of purpoſe in the lap of <hi>Laeda,</hi> and as it were, for his more ſafety crept into her boſom, The Woman not knowing who it was under that ſhape, but holding (as ſhe thought) the <hi>Swan</hi> faſt in her arms, fell aſleep. In the mean while <hi>Jupiter</hi> enjoyed his pleaſure, and having obtained that he came for, betook him again unto his wings; and in memorial of his purpoſe (attained under that form) he placed the <hi>Swan</hi> among the Stars.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ovid</hi> calleth this Conſtellation <hi>Milvius,</hi> the Kite and telleth the Tale thus. The Earth being greatly offended with <hi>Jupiter,</hi> becauſe he had driven <hi>Saturn</hi> his Father out of his kingdom, brought forth a mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous <hi>Bull,</hi> which in his hinder parts was like a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent; and was afterwards called the <hi>Fatal Bull,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the <hi>Deſtinies</hi> had thus decreed, that whoſoever could ſlay him and offer up his Entrails upon an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, ſhould overcome the eternal Gods, <hi>Briareus</hi> that mighty Gyant, and ancient enemy of the Gods, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the <hi>Bull,</hi> and was ready to have offered up his Entrails according to the decree of the <hi>Deſtinies:</hi> but <hi>Jupiter</hi> fearing the event, commanded the Fowls of the Air to ſnatch them away: which although to their power they endeavour'd, yet there was none of them found ſo forward and apt to that action as the <hi>Kite,</hi> and for that cauſe he was accordingly rewarded with a place in Heaven. Some call this Conſtellation <hi>Orvis,</hi> that is the <hi>Bird:</hi> others call it <hi>Vultur Volans,</hi> the <hi>Flying Grype:</hi> It is called <hi>Gallina,</hi> the <hi>Hen.</hi> Unto this Conſtellation do belong two unformed Stars.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:150108:19"/>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>CASSIOPEIA,</hi> She conſiſteth of 13 Stars. This was the Wife of <hi>Cepheus,</hi> and the mother of <hi>Andromeda,</hi> whom <hi>Perſeus</hi> married, and for his ſake was tranſlated into Heaven, as ſome write. others ſay that her beauty being ſingular ſhe waxed ſo proud, that ſhe preferred her ſelf before the <hi>Nereides,</hi> which were the <hi>Nymphs</hi> of the <hi>Sea:</hi> for which cauſe, unto her diſgrace, &amp; the example of all others that in Pride of their hearts would advance themſelves above their betters, ſhe was placed in the Heaven with her head as it were downwards; ſo that in the revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Heavens ſhe ſeemeth to be carried head-long.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>PERSE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> he hath 26 Stars. This was the Son of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> whom he in the likeneſs of a <hi>Golden-ſhower</hi> begat upon <hi>Danae,</hi> the daughter of <hi>Acriſius.</hi> This <hi>Perſeus</hi> coming unto mans eſtate, and being fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with the Sword, Hat, and Wings of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Mercury,</hi> and the Shield of his Siſter <hi>Minerva,</hi> was ſent by his Foſter-father <hi>Polidectes,</hi> to kill the Monſter <hi>Meduſa,</hi> whom he ſlew; and cutting off her head, carried it away with him: But as he was haſting homewards, flying in the Air, he eſpied <hi>Andromeda</hi> the daughter of <hi>Cepheus</hi> and <hi>Caſſiopea,</hi> for the pride of her mother, bound with a Chain unto a Rock, by the Sea ſide, there to be devoured by a Whale: <hi>Perſeus</hi> taking notice and pity of the caſe undertook to fight with the Monſter, upon condition that <hi>Andromeda</hi> might be his Wife, to be ſhort, he deliver'd <hi>Andromeda,</hi> married her, and returning homeward unto the Iſle <hi>Seriphus,</hi> he found there his Grand-father <hi>Acrifius,</hi> whom by miſchance and unadviſedly he ſlew with a quoit: (or as <hi>Ovid</hi> reporteth) with the terrible ſight the horrible head of <hi>Meduſa</hi> not knowing that it was
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:150108:19"/>
his Grand-father: but afterwards underſtanding whom he had ſlain, he pined away through extream ſorrow whereupon <hi>Jupiter</hi> his father pitying his grief took him up into Heaven: and there placed him in that form wherein he overcame <hi>Meduſa</hi> with the Sword in one hand, and the head of <hi>Meduſa</hi> in the other, and the wings of <hi>Mercury</hi> at his Heels. This Conſtellation becauſe of the unluckineſs thereof, is called by Aſtrologers <hi>Cacodaemon (i. e.) <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlucky,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfortunate.</hi> For (as they ſay) they have obſerved it that whatſoever is born under this Conſtellation, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving an evil aſpect, ſhall be ſtricken with Sword, or lofe his Head. <hi>Novidius</hi> ſaith that it is <hi>David</hi> with <hi>Goliah</hi> his head in one hand, and his Sword in the other. The unformed Stars belonging unto this Conſtellation, are three.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RIGA,</hi> the <hi>Wagoner,</hi> or <hi>Carter:</hi> he conſiſteth of 14 Stars: the <hi>Arabians</hi> call him <hi>Alaiot;</hi> the <hi>Greeks Hemochus, (i. e.)</hi> a man holding a bridle in his hand and ſo is he pictur'd. <hi>Eratoſtenes</hi> affirmeth him to be <hi>Ericthonius</hi> King of <hi>Athens,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Vulcan:</hi> who having moſt deformed feet, deviſed firſt the uſe of the Waggon or Chariot, and joyned horſes together to draw the ſame, to the end that he fitting therein might the better conceal his defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities. For which invention, <hi>Jupiter</hi> tranſlated him into the Heavens.</p>
               <p>In this Conſtellation there are two other particular Conſtellations to be noted; whereof the one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth but of one Star alone, which is in the left-ſhoulder of <hi>Auriga,</hi> and is called <hi>Hircus,</hi> or <hi>Capra</hi> the <hi>Goat;</hi> the <hi>Arabians</hi> call it <hi>Alhajoth:</hi> The other conſiſteth of 2 little Stars a little beneath the others,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150108:20"/>
ſtanding as it were in the hand of <hi>Auriga;</hi> this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation is called <hi>Haedi,</hi> the <hi>Kids.</hi> The tale is thus; <hi>Saturn</hi> (as you heard before) had received of the Oracle, that one of his Sons ſhould put him out of his Kingdom, whereupon he determined to devour them all: <hi>Ops</hi> by ſtealth conveyed away <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and ſent him to <hi>Meliſſus</hi> King of <hi>Crete,</hi> to be nouriſhed. <hi>Meliſſus</hi> having 2 daughters, <hi>Amalthaea,</hi> and <hi>Meliſſa,</hi> commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Jupiter</hi> unto their Nurſery; <hi>Amalthaea</hi> had a <hi>Goat</hi> that gave ſuck unto 2 Kids, ſo that by the milk of this <hi>Goat,</hi> ſhe nouriſhed <hi>Jupiter</hi> very well: To requite this her care and courteſie, <hi>Jupiter</hi> (after he had put his Father out of his Kingdom) tranſlated her <hi>Goat</hi> and her two <hi>Kids</hi> into Heaven, and in remembrance of the Nurſe, the <hi>Goat</hi> is called <hi>Capra Amalthaea. Novi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> ſaith, that when Chriſt was born and his birth made manifeſt by the Angels unto the Shepherds, one of them brought with him for a Preſent, a <hi>Goat</hi> and two young <hi>Kids;</hi> which in token of his good will, were placed in Heaven.</p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>OPHI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> or <hi>SERPENTARI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> That is the <hi>Serpent bearer.</hi> This Conſtellation hath no proper name, but is thus entituled, becauſe he holdeth a Serpent in his hands. It containeth 24 Stars. Some ſay that it is <hi>Hercules,</hi> and report the Tale on this manner. <hi>Juno</hi> being a great enemy to <hi>Hercules,</hi> ſent two Snakes to kill him as he lay ſleeping in his Cradle: but <hi>Hercules</hi> being a luſty Child (for <hi>Jupiter</hi> had ſpent two days in begetting him) without much ado ſtrangled them both: In memorial of ſo ſtrange an event, <hi>Jupiter</hi> placed him in the Heavens, with a Serpent in his hands.</p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>SERPENS,</hi> the <hi>Serpent</hi> of <hi>Ophiuchus,</hi> which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150108:20"/>
conſiſteth of 18 Stars. Some ſay that it is one of the Serpents that ſhould have ſlain <hi>Hercules</hi> in his Cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle. <hi>Novidius</hi> ſaith, it is the <hi>Viper</hi> that bit <hi>Paul</hi> by the hand. Others deliver the Tale in theſe words; <hi>Glaucus</hi> the ſon of <hi>Minos</hi> King of <hi>Crete,</hi> was by mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune drowned in a Barrel of Honey: <hi>Minas</hi> his Father craved the help of <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> the Phyſician: and that he might be driven perforce to help the Child, he ſhut him up in a ſecret place, together with the dead Carcaſs: whiles <hi>Eſculapius</hi> ſtood in a great maze with himſelf what were beſt to be done, upon a ſudden there came a Serpent creeping towards him, the which Serpent he ſlew with the Staff which he had in his hand. After this there came another Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in, bringing in his mouth a certain herb, which he laid upon the head of the dead Serpent, whereby he reſtored him unto life again. <hi>Eſculapius</hi> uſing the ſame herb, wrought the ſame effect upon <hi>Glaucus.</hi> Whereupon (after that) <hi>Eſculapius</hi> (whom ſome af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm to be <hi>Ophiucus</hi>) was placed in the Heaven and the <hi>Serpent</hi> with him.</p>
               <p n="15">15. <hi>SAGITA,</hi> or <hi>Telum;</hi> the <hi>Arrow</hi> or <hi>Dart.</hi> This was that Arrow wherewith <hi>Hercules</hi> ſlew the <hi>Eagle</hi> or <hi>Grype</hi> that fed upon the Liver of <hi>Prometheus</hi> being tyed with Chains to the top of Mount <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> and in memorial of that deed, was tranſlated into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. Others will have it to be one of thoſe Arrows which <hi>Hercules</hi> at his death gave unto <hi>Phyloctetes,</hi> upon which the Deſtiny of <hi>Troy</hi> did depend. The whole Conſtellation containeth five Stars.</p>
               <p n="16">16. <hi>AQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ILA,</hi> the <hi>Eagle,</hi> which is called <hi>Vultur Volans,</hi> the <hi>flying Grype.</hi> It hath in it 9 Stars. The Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etical reaſon of this Conſtellation, is this; <hi>Jupiter</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:150108:21"/>
transforming himſelf into the form of an <hi>Eagle</hi> took <hi>Ganimedes</hi> the <hi>Trojan Boy,</hi> whom he greatly loved up into Heaven, and therefore in ſign thereof: (becauſe by that means he performed his purpoſe) he placed the figure of the Eagle in Heaven. There belong unto this Conſtellation 6 Stars (before time) unform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but now brought into the Conſtellation of <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous.</hi> But whereupon that name ſhould come, I know not, except it were that ſome man deviſed it there to curry favour with the Emperour <hi>Adrian,</hi> who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved one <hi>Antinous Bithynicus</hi> ſo well, that he builded a Temple in his honour at <hi>Mantinea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>DELPHIN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> the <hi>Dolphin:</hi> it containeth 10 Stars; yet <hi>Ovid</hi> in his ſecond Book <hi>de Faſtis,</hi> ſaith that it hath but nine. Neither did the ancient Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomers attribute unto it any more, according to the number of the Muſes; becauſe of all other Fiſhes the <hi>Dolphin</hi> is ſaid to be delighted with Muſick. The Tale goeth thus concerning this Conſtellation. When <hi>Neptune</hi> the God of the Sea greatly deſired to match with <hi>Amphitrite,</hi> ſhe being very modeſt and ſhame-faced, hid her ſelf; whereupon he ſent many meſſengers to ſeek her out, among whom, the <hi>Dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phin</hi> by his good hap, did firſt find her; and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded her alſo to match with <hi>Neptune:</hi> For which his good and truſty ſervice, <hi>Neptune</hi> placed him in the Heavens.</p>
               <p>Others ſay, that when <hi>Baccchus</hi> had transformed the Marriners that would have betrayed him, into <hi>Dolphins,</hi> he placed one of them in Heaven, that it might be a leſſon for others to take heed how they carried any one out of his way, contrary both to his deſire, and their own promiſe. <hi>Novidius</hi> referreth
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150108:21"/>
this Conſtellation unto the Fiſh that ſaved <hi>Jonas</hi> from drowning.</p>
               <p n="18">18. <hi>EQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>IC<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LUS,</hi> is the little Horſe, and it conſiſteth of 4 Stars. This Conſtellation is named almoſt of no Writer, ſaving <hi>Ptolomeus,</hi> and <hi>Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> who followed <hi>Ptolemy,</hi> and therefore no certain Tale or Hiſtory is delivered thereof by what means he came into Heaven.</p>
               <p n="19">19. EQUUS ALATUS, the <hi>Winged Horſe,</hi> or <hi>Pegaſus,</hi> it containeth 20 Stars. This Horſe was bred of the blood of <hi>Meduſa,</hi> after that <hi>Perſeus</hi> had cut off her head, and was afterwards taken and tamed by <hi>Bellerophon,</hi> whiles he drank of the River <hi>Pirene</hi> by <hi>Corinth,</hi> and was uſed by him in the conqueſt of <hi>Chi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mera;</hi> after which exploit <hi>Bellerophon</hi> being weary of the earthly affairs, endeavoured to fly up into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. But being amazed in his flight, by looking down to the earth, he fell from his Horſe, <hi>Pegaſus</hi> notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding continuing his courſe (as they feign) en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into Heaven, and there obtained a place among the other Conſtellations.</p>
               <p n="20">20. ANDROMEDA, She conſteth of 23 Stars; but one of them is common both unto her and <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſus.</hi> This was the daughter of <hi>Cepheus</hi> and <hi>Caſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peia,</hi> and the Wife of <hi>Perſeus;</hi> the reaſon why <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerva</hi> or <hi>Jupiter</hi> placed her in the Heavens, is before expreſſed. <hi>Novidius</hi> referreth this Conſtellation unto <hi>Alexandria</hi> the <hi>Virgin,</hi> whom S. <hi>George</hi> through the good help of his Horſe delivered from the <hi>Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="21">21. TRIANGULUM, the <hi>Triangle,</hi> called alſo <hi>Deltoton,</hi> becauſe it is like the fourth Letter of the Greek Alphabet Δ, which they call <hi>Delta;</hi> it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150108:22"/>
of four ſtars. They ſay it was placed in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by <hi>Mercury,</hi> that thereby the head of the <hi>Ram</hi> might be the better known. Others ſay, that it was placed there in honour of the <hi>Geometricians,</hi> among whom, the Triangle is of no ſmall importance. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers affirm, that <hi>Ceres</hi> in times paſt requeſted <hi>Jupiter</hi> that there might be placed in Heaven ſome Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure repreſenting the form of <hi>Sicily</hi> an <hi>Iſland</hi> greatly beloved of <hi>Ceres</hi> for the fruitfulneſs thereof: now this Iſland being triangular (at her requeſt) was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented in the Heaven under that form.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus much concerning the Conſtellations of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Hemiſphere. Now follow the Poetical Stories of the Conſtellations of the Southern Hemiſphere.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Of the <hi>Southern Conſtellations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1 CETUS, the <hi>Whale,</hi> it is alſo called the <hi>Lyon,</hi> or <hi>Bear</hi> of the <hi>Sea.</hi> This is that monſtrous Fiſh that ſhould have devoured <hi>Andromeda,</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing overcome by <hi>Perſeus,</hi> was afterwards tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into Heaven by <hi>Jupiter,</hi> as well for a token of <hi>Perſeus</hi> his manhood, as for the bigneſs of the Fiſh it ſelf. This Conſtellation conſiſteth of 22 Stars.</p>
               <p n="2">2. ORION, this hath 38 Stars. The Poetical reaſon of his tranſlation into the Heavens, ſhall be ſhewn in the <hi>Scorpion</hi> amongſt the Zodiacal Conſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations. The Ancient <hi>Romans</hi> called this Conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <hi>Jugala,</hi> becauſe it is moſt peſtiferous unto Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel, and as it were the very cut-throat of them. There
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150108:22"/>
are bright Stars in his girdle, which we commonly call our <hi>Ladies yard,</hi> or <hi>wand. Novidius,</hi> applying this ſword of <hi>Orion</hi> unto Scripture, will have it to be the Sword of <hi>Saul,</hi> afterwards called <hi>Paul,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he perſecuted the Members of Chriſt: which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Converſion was placed in Heaven. In his left ſhoulder there is a very bright Star, which in <hi>Latine</hi> is called <hi>Bellatrix</hi> the <hi>Warriour,</hi> in the Faeminine Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. I cannot find the reaſon except it be this; that Women born under this Conſtellation ſhall have mighty tongues: the reaſon of the <hi>Ox hide</hi> which he hath in his hand, may be Gathered out of the next ſtory.</p>
               <p n="3">3. FLUVIUS, the <hi>River;</hi> it comprehendeth 34 Stars. It is called by ſome <hi>Eridanus,</hi> or <hi>Pagus;</hi> they ſay that it was placed in Heaven in remembrance of <hi>Phaeton,</hi> who having ſet the whole Earth on fire by reaſon of miſguiding his Father <hi>Phoebus</hi> his Chariot, was ſlain by <hi>Jupiter</hi> with a thunder-bolt, and tumb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling down from Heaven, fell into the River <hi>Eri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danus,</hi> or <hi>Padus,</hi> which the <hi>Italians</hi> call <hi>Po.</hi> Others ſay that it is <hi>Nilus,</hi> and that that figure was placed in Heaven becauſe of the excellency of that River, which by the Divines is called <hi>Gihon,</hi> and is one of the Rivers of <hi>Paradice.</hi> Others call it <hi>Flumen Orionis</hi> the flood of <hi>Orion;</hi> and ſay that it was placed there, to betoken the off-ſpring from whence <hi>Orion</hi> came: for the tale is thus reported of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jupiter, Neptune,</hi> and <hi>Mercury,</hi> travelling upon the Earth in the likneſs of Men, were requeſted by <hi>Hyerus</hi> to take a poor lodging at his houſe for a Night: they being overtaken with the evening, yeild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto his requeſt; <hi>Hyreus</hi> made them good cheer,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150108:23"/>
killing an Ox for their better entertainment: The Gods ſeeing the good heart of the old man, willed him to demand what he would in recompence of his ſo friendly cheer. <hi>Hyerus</hi> and his Wife being old, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted the Gods to gratify them with a Son. They to fulfil his deſire, called for the hide of the <hi>Ox</hi> that was ſlain, and having received it, they put it into the Earth, and made water into it all three toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and covering it, willed <hi>Hyreus</hi> within ten months after to dig it out of the Earth again; which he did and found therein a Man-child; whom he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Ourion, ab Urania,</hi> of piſs; although afterwards by leaving out the ſecond letter, he was named <hi>Orion.</hi> At ſuch time therefore as he was placed in Heaven, this flood was joyned hard to his heels, and the Ox hide wherein the Gods did piſs, was ſet in the left hand, in memorial of his Off-ſpring.</p>
               <p n="4">4. LEPUS, the <hi>Hare,</hi> which conſiſteth of 12 Stars. This Conſtellation was placed in Heaven between the legs of <hi>Orion,</hi> to ſignifie the great delight in hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which he had in his life time: but others think it was a frivolous thing, to ſay that ſo notable a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low as <hi>Orion</hi> would trouble himſelf with ſo ſmall and timorous a Beaſt as the <hi>Hare;</hi> and therefore they tell the tale thus.</p>
               <p>In times paſt there was not a <hi>Hare</hi> left in the Iſle <hi>Leros;</hi> a certain youth therefore of that Iſland, being very deſirous of that kind of beaſt, brought with him from another Country thereabout, an <hi>Hare</hi> great with young which when ſhe had brought forth, they in time became ſo acceptable unto the other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try men, that every one almoſt deſired to have and keep a <hi>Hare.</hi> By reaſon whereof, the number of them
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150108:23"/>
grew to be ſo great, within a ſhort ſpace after, that the whole Iſland became full of <hi>Hares,</hi> ſo that their Maſters were not able to find them meat: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the <hi>Hares</hi> breaking forth into the fields, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured their Corn. Wherefore the Inhabitants being bitten with hunger; joyned together with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and (though with much adoe) deſtroyed the <hi>Hares. Jupiter</hi> therefore placed this Conſtellation in the Heavens; as well to expreſs the exceeding fearfulneſs of the Beaſt, as alſo to teach men this leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; that there is nothing ſo much to be deſired in this life, but that at one time or another bringeth with it more grief than pleaſure. Some ſay, that it was placed in Heaven at the requeſt of <hi>Ganimedes,</hi> who was greatly delighted with hunting the <hi>Hare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. CANIS MAJOR, the <hi>Great Dog,</hi> it conſiſteth of 18 Stars. It is called <hi>Sirius Canis,</hi> becauſe he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth a mighty drought by reaſon of his heat. This is the Conſtellation that giveth name unto the <hi>Canical</hi> or <hi>Dog days;</hi> whoſe beginning and end is not alike in all places, but hath a difference according to the Countrey and time: as in the Time of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> the Phyſitian, who lived before the time of Chriſt 400 years, the <hi>Canicular</hi> days began 13 or 14 of <hi>July.</hi> In the time of <hi>Avicenna,</hi> the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who lived in the year of Lord 1100. the <hi>Canicular</hi> days began the 15, 16, or 17 of <hi>July.</hi> In our Country; they begin about St. <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es-tide,</hi> but we uſe to account from the 6 of <hi>July,</hi> to the 17 of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> which is the time when the Sun beginneth to come near unto and to depart from this Conſtellation.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Novidius</hi> will have it to be referred to <hi>Tobias</hi> Dog which may very well be, becauſe he hath a tail; <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bias</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:150108:24"/>
Dog had one; as a certain fellow once concluded, becauſe it is written that <hi>Tobias</hi> his Dog fawned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Maſter, therefore it is to be noted (ſaid he) that he had a tail. The Poets ſay, that this is the Dog whom <hi>Jupiter</hi> ſet to keep <hi>Europa,</hi> after he had ſtolen her away, and conveyed her into <hi>Creet,</hi> and for his good ſervice was placed in Heaven. Others ſay, that it was one of <hi>Orion</hi> his Dogs. There belong unto this Conſtellation 11 Stars unformed.</p>
               <p n="6">6. CANIS MINOR, the <hi>Leſſer Dog;</hi> this of the Greeks is called <hi>Procyon,</hi> of the Latines <hi>Anteca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis;</hi> it containeth but two Stars. Some ſay, that this was alſo one of <hi>Orion's</hi> Dogs. Others rather affirm it to be <hi>Mera</hi> the Dog of <hi>Origone,</hi> or rather of <hi>Icarius</hi> her Father, of whom mention is made in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation of <hi>Bootes</hi> and <hi>Virgo.</hi> This Dog of meer love to his Maſter, being ſlain, as aforeſaid, threw himſelf into the River <hi>Anygrus,</hi> but was afterward tranſlated into Heaven, with <hi>Origone.</hi> Among the Poets there is great diſſention which of the two ſhould be the Dog of <hi>Origone,</hi> ſome ſaying one, and ſome the other, and therefore they do many times take the one for the other.</p>
               <p n="7">7. ARGO NAVIS, the <hi>Ship Argo</hi> which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehendeth 41 Stars; this is the Ship wherein <hi>Jaſon</hi> did fetch the golden fleece from <hi>Colchis,</hi> which was afterward placed in Heaven as a memorial, not only becauſe of the great Voyage, but alſo, becauſe (as ſome will have it) it was the firſt Ship wherein any man ſailed. Their reaſon why this Ship is not made whole is that thereby men might be put in mind not to deſpair, albeit that their Ship miſcarry'd in ſome part now and then: ſome avouch it to be the <hi>Ark</hi> of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150108:24"/>
                  <hi>Noah. Novidius</hi> ſaith it is the Ship wherein the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> were, when Chriſt appeared unto them walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Sea. In one of the Oars of this Ship there is a great Star, called <hi>Canopus,</hi> or <hi>Canobus,</hi> which the <hi>Arabians</hi> called <hi>Shuel,</hi> as it were a bone-fire, becauſe of the greatneſs thereof. It is not ſeen in <hi>Italy,</hi> nor in any Country on this ſide of <hi>Italy:</hi> Some ſay that <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nobus</hi> the Maſter of <hi>Menelaus,</hi> his Ship was transfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med into this Star.</p>
               <p n="8">8. HYDRA, the <hi>Hydra,</hi> that hath 25 Stars and two unformed.</p>
               <p n="9">9. CRATER, the <hi>Cup,</hi> or <hi>Standing-piece;</hi> that hath ſeven Stars, ſome ſay that this was the Cup where in <hi>Tagathon,</hi> that is the chief God, ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Stuff whereof he made the Souls of Men.</p>
               <p n="10">10. CORVUS, the <hi>Crow;</hi> this hath ſeven Stars. Theſe 3 Conſtellations are to be joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, becauſe they depend upon one Hiſtory, which is this. Upon a time <hi>Apollo</hi> made a ſolemn feaſt to <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter,</hi> and wanting water to ſerve his turn, he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered a Cup to the <hi>Crow</hi> (the bird wherein he chiefly delighted) and ſent him to fetch water therein. The <hi>Crow</hi> flying towards the River, eſpied a Fig-tree, fell in hand with the Figs, and abode there till they were ripe: In the end when, he had fed his fill of them, and ſatisfied his longing, he bethought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of his errand, and by reaſon of his long delay, fearing a Check, he caught up a ſnake in his bill, brought it to <hi>Apollo,</hi> and told him that the ſnake would not let him fill the <hi>Cup</hi> with water, <hi>Apollo</hi> ſeeing the impudence of the bird, gave him this gift, that as long as the Figs were not ripe upon the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150108:25"/>
Tree ſo long he ſhould never drink: and for a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morial of the ſilly excuſe that ſhe made, he placed both the <hi>Crow, Cup,</hi> and <hi>Snake,</hi> in Heaven.</p>
               <p n="11">11. CENTAURUS, the <hi>Centaure,</hi> which comprehendeth 37 Stars. Some ſay, that this is <hi>Typhon,</hi> others call him <hi>Chiron,</hi> the Schoolmaſter of thoſe three excellent men, <hi>Hercules, Achilles,</hi> and <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culapius:</hi> unto <hi>Hercules</hi> he read <hi>Aſtronomy,</hi> he trained <hi>Achilles</hi> in <hi>Muſick,</hi> and <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> in <hi>Phyſick:</hi> and for his upright life he was turned into this Conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Yet <hi>Virgil</hi> calleth <hi>Sagittarius</hi> by the name of <hi>Chiron.</hi> In the hinder feet of this Conſtellaton, thoſe Stars are ſet which are called the <hi>Croſiers,</hi> appearing to the Marriners as they ſail towards the South Sea, in the form of a Croſs, whereupon they have their name. The four Stars which are in the Garniſh of the <hi>Centaurs</hi> Spear, are accounted by <hi>Proclus</hi> as a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Conſtellation, and are called by him <hi>Thyrſilochus</hi> which was a Spear compaſſed about with vine leaves: but they are called by <hi>Copernicus,</hi> and <hi>Clavius,</hi> and other Aſtronomers, the Stars of his Target. It ſhould ſeem that they were deceived by the old tranſlation of <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> wherein <hi>Scutum</hi> is put for <hi>Haſta (i.e.)</hi> the Target, for the Spear, as it is well noted by our Country-man Mr. <hi>R. Record,</hi> in his Book entituled <hi>The Caſtle of Knowledge.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. LUPUS, the <hi>Wolfe,</hi> or the beaſt which the <hi>Centaur</hi> holdeth in his hand, contaneth 19 Stars; the Poetical reaſon is this, <hi>Chiron</hi> the <hi>Centaur</hi> being a juſt man, was greatly given to the worſhip of the Gods: for which thing, that it might be notified to all poſterity, they placed him by this beaſt, which he ſeemeth to ſtick and thruſt through with his
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150108:25"/>
Spear (as it were) ready to kill for Sacrifice.</p>
               <p n="13">13. ARA, the <hi>Altar,</hi> it is alſo called <hi>Lar,</hi> or <hi>Thuribulum (i. e.)</hi> a Chimney with the fire, or a Cenſor. It conſiſteth of ſeven Stars, and is affirmed of ſome Poets to be the <hi>Altar</hi> whereon the <hi>Centaur</hi> was wont to offer up his ſacrifice. But others tell the tale thus. When as the great Gyants called the <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans</hi> laboured as much as might be to pull <hi>Jupiter</hi> out of Heaven, the Gods thought it good to lay their heads together, to adviſe what was beſt to be done: Their concluſion was, that they ſhould all with one conſent join hands together to keep out ſuch fellows, and that this their league might be confirmed, and throughly ratified, they cauſed the <hi>Cyclops</hi> (which were workmen of <hi>Vulcan</hi>) to make them an Altar: about this Altar all the Gods aſſembled, and there ſware, that with one conſent they would withſtand their enemies; afterwards, having gotten the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it pleaſed them to place this Altar in Heaven as a memorial of their League, and a token of that good which unity doth breed.</p>
               <p n="14">14. CORONA AUSTRINA, the <hi>South Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> it hath 13 Stars. Some ſay that it is ſome tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling <hi>Garland</hi> which <hi>Sagittarius</hi> was wont to wear, but he caſt it away from him in jeſt, and therefore it was placed between his legs; others call it the Wheel of <hi>Ixon,</hi> whereupon he was tormented for that great diſcourteſie he would have offered unto <hi>Juno,</hi> thinking indeed to have gotten up her Belly: but <hi>Jupiter</hi> ſeeing the impudency of the man, tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled him out of Heaven (where by the licenſe of the gods he was ſometimes admitted as a gueſt) into Hell there to be continually tormented upon a Wheel:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150108:26"/>
The Figure of which Wheel was afterwards placed in Heaven, to teach men to take heed how they be too ſaucie to make ſuch courteous proffers unto other mens wives. The Greeks call this Conſtellation by the name of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>raniſcus,</hi> becauſe of the Figure there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: For it repreſenteth the palate or roof of the mouth, which they call <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>raniſcus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="15">15. The laſt is PISCIS AUSTRINUS, or <hi>Notius,</hi> the <hi>South Fiſh,</hi> which comprehendeth 11 Stars, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that which is in the mouth thereof, belonging to the water, which runneth from <hi>Aquarius,</hi> and is called by the <hi>Arabians Fomahant.</hi> The reaſon why this Fiſh was placed in the Heaven, is uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain: yet ſome affirm, that the daughter of <hi>Venus</hi> going into a water to waſh her ſelf, was ſuddenly transformed into a Fiſh the which Fiſh was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards tranſlated into Heaven. The unformed Stars belonging unto this Conſtellation are ſix.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus much concerning the Conſtellation of the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern and Southern Hemiſpheres; now follow the Poeti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Stories of the Zodiacal Conſtellations.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Of the <hi>Zodiacal Conſtellations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>ARIES,</hi> the <hi>Ram,</hi> it is called by the Greeks <hi>Crios,</hi> it containeth in it 13 Stars, which were brought into this Conſtellation by <hi>Thyeſtes,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Pelops,</hi> and brother of <hi>Acreus.</hi> This is the <hi>Ram,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which <hi>Phrixus,</hi> and <hi>Helle</hi> his ſiſter, the children of <hi>Athamas</hi> did ſit, when they fled from their ſtep-mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:150108:26"/>
                  <hi>Ino,</hi> over the Sea of <hi>Helleſpont:</hi> which <hi>Ram</hi> was afterwards for his good ſervice, tranſlated to Heaven ven by <hi>Jupiter</hi> Others ſay, that it was that <hi>Ram</hi> which brought <hi>Bacchus</hi> unto the ſpring of water, when through drought he was likely to have periſhed in the deſert of <hi>Lybia. Novidius</hi> will have this to be the <hi>Ram,</hi> which <hi>Abraham</hi> offered up inſtead of his Son <hi>Iſaac.</hi> The Star that is firſt in the head of the <hi>Ram,</hi> is that from whence our later Aſtronomers do account the Longitude of all the reſt, and it is diſtant from the head of <hi>Aries,</hi> in the tenth Sphere, 27 degrees 53 minutes. The unformed Stars belonging unto this Conſtellation, are five.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>TA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> the <hi>Bull,</hi> which conſiſteth of 23 Stars. This was tranſlated into Heaven in memorial of the Rape committed by <hi>Jupiter</hi> on <hi>Europa</hi> the daughter of <hi>Agenor,</hi> King of <hi>Sidon;</hi> whom <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the likeneſs of a white Bull ſtole away, and tranſport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into <hi>Candia.</hi> Others ſay, That it was <hi>Io</hi> the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Inacus,</hi> whom <hi>Jupiter</hi> loved, and turned into the form of a Cow, to the intent that <hi>Juno</hi> coming at unawares, ſhould not perceive what a part he had played: <hi>Jupiter</hi> afterward in memorial of that crafty conveyance, placed that Figure in Heaven; The rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why the Poets name not certainly whether it be a Cow or a Bull, is becauſe it wanteth the hinder parts; yet of the moſt of them it is called a <hi>Bull.</hi> In the Neck of the <hi>Bull</hi> there are certain Stars ſtanding together in a cluſter, which are commonly called the <hi>ſeven Stars;</hi> although there can hardly be diſcerned any more than ſix, theſe are reported to be the ſeven daughters of <hi>Atlas,</hi> called <hi>Atlantiades,</hi> whereof 6 had company with the immortal Gods, but the 7th.
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:150108:27"/>
(whoſe name was <hi>Merope</hi>) being married unto <hi>Syſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> a mortal man, did therefore withdraw and hide her ſelf, as being aſhamed that ſhe was not ſo fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate in matching herſelf as her ſiſters were. Some ſay that that ſtar which is wanting is <hi>Electra,</hi> eldeſt Daughter of <hi>Atlas,</hi> and that therefore it is ſo dim, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe could not abide to behold the deſtruction of <hi>Troy;</hi> but at that time and ever ſince, ſhe hid her face. The reaſon why they were taken up into Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, was their great pity towards their Father, whoſe miſhap they bewailed with continual tears. Others ſay, that whereas they had vowed perpetual Virgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and were in danger to loſe it, by reaſon of <hi>Orion,</hi> who greatly aſſailed them, being overtaken with their love; they requeſted <hi>Jupiter</hi> to ſtand their friend; who tranſlated them into Stars, and placed them in that part of Heaven. The Poets call them <hi>Pleiades,</hi> becauſe when they riſe with the Sun, the Mariners may commit themſelves to the Sea. Others will have them to be ſo termed <hi>a pluendo,</hi> becauſe they procure rain. Others give them this name, of the Greek word <hi>Cleiones,</hi> becauſe they be many in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber; they be alſo called <hi>Virgiliae,</hi> becauſe they riſe with the Sun in the <hi>Spring time:</hi> likewiſe <hi>Athoraiae,</hi> becauſe they ſtand ſo thick together. Our men call them by the name of the <hi>ſeven Stars,</hi> or <hi>Brood Hen.</hi> The Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomers note this as a ſpecial thing concerning theſe ſtars, that when the Moon and theſe Stars do meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, the eyes are not to be medled withal, or cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red if they before: their reaſon is, becauſe they be of the nature of <hi>Mars</hi> and the <hi>Moon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreover, there be five ſtars in the face of the <hi>Bull,</hi> repreſenting the form of the <hi>Roman</hi> letter V, whereof
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:150108:27"/>
one (which is the greateſt) is called the <hi>Bulls Eye,</hi> They be called <hi>Hyades,</hi> and were alſo the daughters of <hi>Atlas,</hi> who ſo long bewailed the death of <hi>Hyas</hi> their Brother, ſlain by a <hi>Lyon,</hi> that they died for ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and were afterwards placed in Heaven, for a memorial of that great love they bare to their Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. The ancient <hi>Romans</hi> call the <hi>Bulls Eye Parilici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> or <hi>Palelicium;</hi> of <hi>Pales</hi> their goddeſs, whoſe feaſt they celebrated after the conjunction of this Star and the Sun. The unformed Stars belonging unto this Conſtellation, are eleven.</p>
               <p n="3">3. GEMINI, the <hi>Twins</hi> conſiſteth of 18 ſtars. The Poets ſay, they are <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> the ſons of <hi>Leda,</hi> brethren moſt loving, whom therefore <hi>Jupiter</hi> tranſlated into Heaven. Some ſay that one of them is <hi>Apollo,</hi> and the other <hi>Hercules:</hi> but the moſt affirm the former. The unformed Stars of this Conſtellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on are ſeven, whereof one is called <hi>Tropus,</hi> becauſe it is placed next before the foot of <hi>Caſtor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. CANCER, the <hi>Crab,</hi> it hath 9 Stars. This is that <hi>Crab</hi> which bit <hi>Hercules</hi> by the heel as he fought with the Serpent <hi>Hydra</hi> in the Fen <hi>Lerna,</hi> and for his forward ſervice, was placed in Heaven by <hi>Juno,</hi> the utter enemy of <hi>Hercules.</hi> In this Conſtellation there are Stars much ſpoken of by the Poets; although they be but ſmall, whereof one is called the <hi>Crib,</hi> other two are the two <hi>Aſſes,</hi> whereof one was the <hi>Aſs</hi> of <hi>Bacchus,</hi> the other of <hi>Vulcan,</hi> whereon they rode to Battel, when as the Gyants made War with the Gods; with whoſe braying and ſtrange noiſe, the Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ants were ſo ſcared upon the ſudden, that they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook the field, and fled. The Gods getting the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, in triumphing manner tranſlated both the <hi>Aſſes,</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:150108:28"/>
and their manger into Heaven. The unformed Stars of this Conſtellation are four. It is called <hi>animal Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trogradum,</hi> for when the Sun cometh into this Sign, he maketh Retrogradation.</p>
               <p n="5">5. LEO, the <hi>Lyon;</hi> it hath 27 Stars, this is that <hi>Lion</hi> which <hi>Hercules</hi> overcame in the wood <hi>Nemaea,</hi> and was placed in Heaven in remembrance of ſo notable a deed. <hi>Novidius</hi> ſaith, this was one of the <hi>Lyons</hi> that were in the den into which <hi>Daniel</hi> was caſt, and was therefore placed in Heaven, becauſe of all other he was moſt friendly unto <hi>Daniel.</hi> In the breaſt of this Conſtellation is that notable great Star, the light whereof is ſuch, as that therefore it is called by A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtronomers <hi>Bazileus</hi> or <hi>Regulus (i e.)</hi> the <hi>Viceroy</hi> or little King among the reſt: The unformed Stars be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the <hi>Lyon</hi> are eight, whereof three make the Conſtellation which is now called <hi>Coma Berenices</hi> that is, the hair of <hi>Berenice.</hi> This Conſtellation was firſt found out and invented by <hi>Canon</hi> the Mathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tician, but deſcribed by <hi>Calimachus</hi> the Poet. The occaſion of the ſtory was this. <hi>Ptolomeus Euergetes</hi> having married his ſiſter <hi>Berenice,</hi> was ſhortly after enforced to depart from her, by reaſon of the Wars he had begun in <hi>Aſia:</hi> whereupon <hi>Berenice</hi> made this Vow, that if he returned home again in ſafety, ſhe would offer up her hair in <hi>Venus</hi> Temple. <hi>Ptolomy</hi> returned ſafe; and <hi>Berenice,</hi> according to her Vow, cut off her hair and hung it up. After certain days, the hair was not to be found; whereupon <hi>Ptolomy</hi> the King was greatly diſpleaſed; but <hi>Canon,</hi> to pleaſe the humor of the King, and to curry favour with him, perſwaded him that <hi>Venus</hi> had conveyed the Hair into Heaven. <hi>Canon</hi> attributeth ſeven Stars unto
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150108:28"/>
it, but <hi>Ptolomy</hi> allotteth it but three, becauſe the other be inſenſible.</p>
               <p n="6">6. VIRGO, the <hi>Virgin,</hi> it hath 26 Stars. This is affirmed to be Juſtice, which among all the Gods ſometime living upon the Earth, did laſt of all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the ſame, becauſe of the wickedneſs that began to multiply therein, and choſe this place for her ſeat in Heaven.</p>
               <p>Others ſay, that it was <hi>Aſtrea,</hi> the daughter of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreus,</hi> one of the Gyants that were called <hi>Titans,</hi> who fighting againſt the Gods, <hi>Aſtraea</hi> took their parts againſt her own Father, and was therefore after her death commended unto the Heavens, and made one of the 12 Signs.</p>
               <p>Others ſay, that it was <hi>Origone,</hi> the daughter of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carius,</hi> who for that her Father was ſlain by certain drunken men, for very grief thereof hanged her ſelf: but <hi>Jupiter</hi> taking pity of the <hi>Virgin</hi> for her natural affection, tranſlated her into Heaven.</p>
               <p>In her right wing there is one Star of ſpecial note, which by the Aſtronomers is called <hi>Vindemiaetor, (i.e.)</hi> the gatherer of Grapes. This was <hi>Ampulos</hi> the ſon of a Satyr and a Nymph, and greatly beloved of <hi>Bac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus</hi> unto whom in token of his love, <hi>Bacchus</hi> gave a ſingular fair Vine, planted at the foot of an Elm (as the manner was in old time.) But <hi>Ampelos</hi> in Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt gathering Grapes, and taking little heed to his footing, fell down out of the Vine, and brake his neck. <hi>Bacchus</hi> in memorial of his former affection, tranſlated him into Heaven, and made him one of the principal Stars in this Conſtellation. There is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother great Star in the hand of the <hi>Virgin,</hi> called of the Latines <hi>Spica,</hi> of the Greeks <hi>Stachus,</hi> of the Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:150108:29"/>
                  <hi>Azimech (i.e.)</hi> the <hi>Ear of Corn:</hi> whereby they ſignifie, that when the Sun cometh to this Sign, the Corn waxeth ripe. <hi>Albumazar</hi> the <hi>Arabian,</hi> and <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidius,</hi> take this Conſtellation for the Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi> The unformed Stars in this Conſtellation are ſix.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>LIBRA</hi> the <hi>Ballance,</hi> it containeth eight Stars, <hi>Cicero</hi> calleth <hi>Jugum</hi> the <hi>Yoke,</hi> and here it is to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that the ancient Aſtronomers that firſt ſet down the number of the Conſtellations contained in the Zodiack, did account but eleven therein, ſo that the Sign, which now is called <hi>Libra,</hi> was heretofore cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Chelai,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>the Claws of the Scorpion,</hi> which poſſeſſeth the ſpace of two whole Signs. But the latter Aſtronomers, being deſirous to have 12 Signs in the Zodiack, called thoſe eight, whereof the <hi>Claws of the Scorpion</hi> do conſiſt, by the name of <hi>Libra,</hi> not that there was any Poetical Fiction to induce them thereto, but only moved by this reaſon, becauſe the Sun joyning with this Conſtellation, the Day and the Night are of an equal length, and are (as it were) equally poized in a pair of Ballances. Yet (as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) ſome will have this to be the Ballance, wherein Juſtice, called alſo <hi>Aſtraea,</hi> weighed the deeds of mortal men, and therein preſented them unto <hi>Jupiter.</hi> It hath 9 unformed Stars appertaining unto it.</p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>SCORPIO,</hi> the <hi>Scorpion,</hi> called of the <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bians, Alatrab;</hi> of <hi>Cicero, Nepa.</hi> It conſiſteth of 21 Stars. The Fiction is thus; <hi>Orion</hi> the ſon of <hi>Hyreus</hi> greatly beloved of <hi>Diana,</hi> was wont to make his boaſt: that he was able to overcome what Beaſt ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver was bred upon the Earth: the Earth being moved with this ſpeech brought forth the <hi>Scorpion,</hi> whereby
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:150108:29"/>
                  <hi>Orion</hi> was ſtung to death. <hi>Jupiter</hi> thereupon (at the requeſt of the Earth) tranſlated both the <hi>Scorpion</hi> and <hi>Orion</hi> into Heaven; to make it a leſſon for ever, for mortal men not to truſt too much unto their own ſtrength; and to the end he might ſignify the great enmity between them, he placed them ſo in Heaven, that whenſoever the one ariſeth, the other ſetteth; and they are never both of them ſeen together above the Horizon at once: <hi>Gulielmus Poſtellus</hi> will have it to be the <hi>Serpent</hi> which beguiled <hi>Eve</hi> in <hi>Paradiſe.</hi> The unformed Stars about this <hi>Scorpion</hi> are three.</p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>SAGITTARI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> the <hi>Archer.</hi> It hath 31 Stars. Touching this Sign, there are among the Poets ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and ſundry opinions. Some ſay that it is <hi>Crocus,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Paphene,</hi> that was Nurſe unto the Muſes. This <hi>Crocus</hi> was ſo forward in learning of the Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sciences, and in the practice of feats of Activity, that the Muſes entreated <hi>Jupiter</hi> that he might have a place in Heaven. To whoſe requeſt <hi>Jupiter</hi> incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, made him one of the 12 Signs: And to the end that he might expreſs the excellent qualities of the Man; he made his hinder parts like unto a Horſe, thereby to ſignifie his ſingular knowledge in Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip: and by his Bow and Arrow, he declared the ſharpneſs of his Wit. Whereupon the Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers have this conceit, that he that is born under <hi>Sagittarius,</hi> ſhall attain to the knowledge of many Arts, and be of prompt wit, and great courage. <hi>Virgil</hi> affirmeth this to be <hi>Chiron</hi> the <hi>Centaur,</hi> who for his ſingular Learning and Juſtice was made the Maſter of <hi>Achilles.</hi> At which time <hi>Hercules</hi> coming to viſit him (for he had heard both of the worthineſs of the School-maſter, and of the great hopes of the Scholar)
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:150108:30"/>
brought with him his quiver of Arrows dipped in the blood of the Serpent <hi>Hydra;</hi> but <hi>Chiron</hi> being deſirous to ſee his ſhafts, and not taking heed of them being in his hand, let one of them fall upon his foot, and being greatly tormented, not only by the anguiſh of the Poyſon working in the Wound, but much more becauſe he knew himſelf to be immortal, and his wound not to be recovered by Medicine, he was enforced to make requeſt unto the Gods, that he might be taken out of the World, who pitying his caſe, took him up into Heaven, and made him one of the 12 Signs.</p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>CAPRICORN<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> the <hi>Goat,</hi> it conſiſteth of 28 Stars. The Poets ſay, that this was <hi>Pan</hi> the God of the Shepherds, of whom they feign in this manner: The Gods having War with the Gyants, gathered themſelves together into <hi>Aegypt, Typhon</hi> the Gyant purſued them thither, whereby the Gods were brought into a quandary, that well was he that by changing his ſhape might ſhift for himſelf. <hi>Jupiter</hi> turned himſelf into a <hi>Ram: Apollo</hi> became a <hi>Crow: Bacchus</hi> a <hi>Goat: Diana</hi> lurked under the form of a <hi>Cat: Juno</hi> transformed her ſelf into a <hi>Cow: Venus</hi> into a <hi>Fiſh: Pan</hi> leaping into the River <hi>Nilus,</hi> turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the upper part of his body into a <hi>Goat,</hi> and the lower part into a <hi>Fiſh. Jupiter</hi> wondring at the ſtrange device, would needs have that Image and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture tranſlated into Heaven, and made one of the 12 Signs. In that the hinder part of this Sign is like a Fiſh. It betokeneth that the latter part of the month wherein the Sun poſſeſſeth this Sign, inclineth unto Rain.</p>
               <p n="11">11. <hi>AQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ARI<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S,</hi> the <hi>Waterman:</hi> it hath 42 Stars,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:150108:30"/>
whereof ſome make the Figure of the Man: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome the Water-pot; and ſome, the ſtream of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that runneth out of the pot. This is feigned to be <hi>Ganimedes</hi> the <hi>Trojan,</hi> the ſon of <hi>Oros</hi> and <hi>Callirhoe,</hi> whom <hi>Jupiter</hi> did greatly love for his excellent fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and beauty, and by the ſervice of his Eagle car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him up into Heaven, where he made him his Cup-bearer, and called him <hi>Aquarius.</hi> Others not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding think it to be <hi>Deucalion</hi> the ſon of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metheus</hi> whom the Gods tranſlated into Heaven, in remembrance of that mighty deluge which hapned in his time; whereby mankind was almoſt utterly ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away from the face of the earth. The unformed ſtars belonging unto this Sign are three.</p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>PISCES,</hi> the <hi>Fiſhes:</hi> theſe together with the line that knitteth them together, contain 24 Stars. The Poets ſay, that <hi>Venus</hi> and <hi>Cupid</hi> her ſon coming upon a certain time unto the River <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and ſitting upon the bank thereof, upon a ſudden eſpied <hi>Typhon</hi> the <hi>Gyant,</hi> that mighty and fearful enemy of the gods coming towards them; upon whoſe ſight, they being ſtricken with exceeding fear, lept into the River, where they were received by two Fiſhes, and by them ſaved from drowning. <hi>Venus</hi> for this good turn, tranſlated them into Heaven. <hi>Gulielmus Poſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus</hi> would have them to be the two Fiſhes wherewith Chriſt fed the 5000 Men. The unformed Stars of this Conſtellation are four.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thus have I briefly run over the Poetical reaſons of the Conſtellations: It remains now that I ſpeak of the</hi> Milky Way.</p>
               <p>VIA LACTEA, or <hi>Circulus Lacteus;</hi> by the Latines ſo called; and by the <hi>Greeks Galaxia;</hi> and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:150108:31"/>
by the Engliſh the <hi>Milkey Way.</hi> It is a broad white Circle that is ſeen in the Heaven: In the North He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſphere, it beginneth at <hi>Cancer,</hi> on each ſide the head thereof, and paſſeth by <hi>Auriga, Perſeus, Caſſiopeia,</hi> the <hi>Swan,</hi> and the head of <hi>Capricorn,</hi> the tail of <hi>Scorpio,</hi> the feet of <hi>Centaeur, Argo</hi> the <hi>Ship,</hi> and ſo to the head of <hi>Cancer.</hi> Some in a ſporting manner do call it <hi>Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-ſtreet,</hi> but why they call it ſo, I cannot tell; except it be in regard of the narrowneſs that it ſeemeth to have; or elſe in reſpect of that great high way that lyeth between <hi>Dover</hi> and St. <hi>Albons,</hi> which is called by our men <hi>Watling-ſtreet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Ovid</hi> ſaith, it is the great Cauſey, and High-way that leadeth unto the Pallace of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> but he alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the cauſe of the whiteneſs; belike he would have us imagine that it is made of White Marble.</p>
               <p>Others therefore alledg theſe cauſes: <hi>Jupiter</hi> having begotten <hi>Mercury</hi> of <hi>Maia</hi> the daughter of <hi>Atlas,</hi> brought the child when he was born, to the breaſt of <hi>Juno</hi> lying aſleep: But <hi>Juno</hi> awaking threw the child out of her lap, and let the milk run out of her breaſt in ſuch abundance, that (ſpreading it ſelf about the Heaven) it made that Circle which we ſee. Others ſay, that it was not <hi>Mercury,</hi> but <hi>Hercules;</hi> and that <hi>Juno</hi> did not let the milk run out of her breaſt, but that <hi>Hercules</hi> ſuckt them ſo earneſtly, that his mouth run over, and ſo this Circle was made.</p>
               <p>Others ſay, that <hi>Saturn</hi> being deſirous to devour his children, his wife <hi>Ops</hi> preſented him with a ſtone wrapped in a clout, inſtead of his Child: This ſtone ſtuck ſo faſt in <hi>Saturn</hi>'s Throat as he would have ſwallowed it, that without doubt he had therewith been choaked, had he not been relieved by his wife:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:150108:31"/>
who by preſſing the milk out of her breaſts ſaved his life: the milk that miſſed his mouth (whereof you muſt ſuppoſe ſome ſufficient quantity) fell on the Heavens, and running along made this Circle.</p>
               <p>Dr. <hi>Hood Commenting upon Conſtellations ſaith;</hi> the Stars are brought into Conſtellations, for Inſtruction ſake, things cannot be taught without names; to give a name to every Star had been troubleſome to the Maſter, and for the Scholar; for the Maſter to deviſe, and for the Scholar to remember; and therefore the Aſtronomers have reduced many Stars into one Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtellation; that thereby they may tell the better where to ſeek them; and being ſought, how to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs them. Now the Aſtronomers did bring them into theſe Figures, and not into other, being moved thereto by theſe three reaſons: firſt, theſe Figures expreſs ſome properties of the Stars that are in them; as thoſe in the <hi>Ram</hi> to be hot and dry; <hi>Andro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meda</hi> chained betokeneth impriſonment, the head of <hi>Meduſa</hi> cut off ſignifieth the loſs of that part: <hi>Orion</hi> with his terrible and threatning geſture, importeth tempeſt and terrible effects. The <hi>Serpent,</hi> the <hi>Scorpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and the <hi>Dragon,</hi> ſignifie Poyſon: The <hi>Bull</hi> inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ateth a melancholy paſſion: The <hi>Bear</hi> inferreth cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Secondly, the Stars (if not preciſely, yet after a ſort) do repreſent ſuch a Figure, and therefore that Figure was aſſigned them, as for example, the <hi>Crown,</hi> both North and South, the <hi>Scorpion</hi> and <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle,</hi> repreſent the figures which they have. The third cauſe was the continuance of the memory of ſome notable Men, who either in regard of their ſingular pains taken in Aſtronomy, or in regard of ſome other notable deed, had well deſerved of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:150108:32"/>
               <p>The firſt Author of every particular Conſtellation is uncertain; yet are they of great antiquity; we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them from <hi>Ptolomy,</hi> and he followed the <hi>Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicks;</hi> ſo that their antiquity is great. Moreover, we may perceive them to be ancient by the Scriptures, and by the Poets. In the 38 Chapter of <hi>Job</hi> there is mention made of the <hi>Pleiades, Orion,</hi> and <hi>Arcturus,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mazzaroth,</hi> which ſome interpret the 12 Signs: <hi>Job</hi> lived in the time of <hi>Abraham,</hi> as <hi>Syderocrates</hi> maketh mention in his Book <hi>de Commenſurandis locorum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now beſides all this, touching the reaſon of inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of theſe Conſtellations, the Poets in ſetting forth thoſe Stories, had this purpoſe, to make men fall in love with Aſtronomy: When <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> could not get the people of <hi>Athens</hi> to hear him in a matter of great moment, and profitable to the Common-wealth he began to tell them a Tale of a fellow that ſold an Aſs; by which Tale he ſo wrought on the <hi>Atheni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that they were both willing to hear his whole O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and to put in practiſe that whereunto he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted them. The like intent had the Poets in theſe Stories: They ſaw that Aſtronomy being for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity ſingular in the life of Man, was almoſt of all men utterly neglected: Hereupon they began to ſet forth that Art under theſe Fictions; that thereby ſuch as could not be perſwaded by commodity, might by the Pleaſure be induced to take a view of theſe matters, and thereby at length fall in love with them. For commonly note this, that he that is ready to read the Stories, cannot content himſelf therewith, but deſireth alſo to know the Conſtellations, or at leaſt wiſe ſome principal Star therein.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="advert">
            <pb facs="tcp:150108:32"/>
            <p>At the place aforeſaid, you may alſo have all manner of <hi>Maps, Sea-Plats, Drafts, Mathematical Books, Inſtruments,</hi> &amp;c. at the loweſt Prizes.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:150108:33"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:150108:33"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
